This is a lot of ones and zeros.
هذه غابة من الآحاد والأصفار.
It's what we call binary information.
هذا ما نسميه بالمعلومات الثنائية.
This is how computers talk.
هكذا تتكلم الحواسيب.
It's how they store information.
وهذه طريقتها لتخزين المعلومات.
It's how computers think.
وطريقتها في التفكير.
It's how computers do
وطريقتها في القيام بكل ما تفعله.
I'm a cybersecurity researcher,
أنا باحث في الأمن السَّيبِرانِي،
which means my job is to sit down with this information
أي أن مهمتي هي الجلوس أمام هذه المعلومات
and try to make sense of it,
ومحاولة فهم ما تعنيه،
to try to understand what all the ones and zeroes mean.
محاولة فهم ما تعنيه تلك الآحاد والأصفار.
Unfortunately for me, we're not just talking
لسوء حظي، نحن لا نتحدث فقط
about the ones and zeros I have on the screen here.
عن الآحاد والأصفار الظاهرة هنا على الشاشة.
We're not just talking about a few pages of ones and zeros.
أو عن بضع صفحات من الآحاد والأصفار.
We're talking about billions and billions
بل نتحدث عن مليارات ومليارات
of ones and zeros,
من الآحاد والأصفار،
more than anyone could possibly comprehend.
أكثر مما يمكن أن يفهمه أي شخص.
Now, as exciting as that sounds,
رغم أنها قد تبدو مثيرة،
when I first started doing cyber —
إلا أني عندما بدأت العمل في السيبرانية--
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)--
when I first started doing cyber, I wasn't sure
عندما بدأت العمل في السيبرانية،
that sifting through ones and zeros
لم أكن متأكدا أني أرغب
was what I wanted to do with the rest of my life,
في قضاء حياتي أغربل الآحاد والأصفار،
because in my mind, cyber
لأني كنت أعتقد، أن السيبرانية
was keeping viruses off of my grandma's computer,
كانت تعني حماية حاسوب جدتي من الفيروسات،
it was keeping people's Myspace pages from being hacked,
ومن قرصنة صفحات ماي سبيس،
and maybe, maybe on my most glorious day,
وربما، ربما في يوم مجدي،
it was keeping someone's credit card information from being stolen.
أحمي معلومات بطاقة اعتماد أحدهم من السرقة.
Those are important things,
تلك أشياء مهمة،
but that's not how I wanted to spend my life.
ولكن لم تكن تلك هي الحياة التي أريد.
But after 30 minutes of work
ولكن بعد 30 دقيقة من العمل
as a defense contractor,
كمقاول دفاع،
I soon found out that my idea of cyber
علمت فورا أن فكرتي عن السيبرانية
was a little bit off.
كانت إلى حد ما خاطئة.
In fact, in terms of national security,
في الواقع، من حيث الأمن الوطني،
keeping viruses off of my grandma's computer
حماية حاسوب جدتي من الفيروسات
was surprisingly low on their priority list.
كان آخر أولوياتهم، غريب!
And the reason for that is cyber
وذلك لأن السيبرانية أكبر من تلك الأشياء.
Cyber is an integral part of all of our lives,
السيبرانية هي جزء لا يتجزء من حياتنا،
because computers are an integral part of all of our lives,
لأن الحواسيب هي جزء لا يتجزء من حياتنا،
even if you don't own a computer.
حتى وإن لم يكن لديكم حاسوب.
Computers control everything in your car,
الحواسيب تتحكم بكل شيء في سياراتكم،
from your GPS to your airbags.
من نظام تحديد الموقع حتى الوسائد الهوائية.
They control your phone.
إنها تتحكم في هواتفكم.
They're the reason you can call 911
وبفضلها يُرَدُّ عليكم عند الاتصال بالطوارئ
They control our nation's entire infrastructure.
إنها تتحكم بجميع البنيات التحتية ببلدنا.
They're the reason you have electricity,
إنها السبب في حصولكم على الكهرباء،
heat, clean water, food.
والحرارة والماء النقي والطعام.
Computers control our military equipment,
الحواسيب تتحكم بمُعِدَّاتِنَا العسكرية،
everything from missile silos to satellites
بكل شيء، من صوامع الصواريخ
to nuclear defense networks.
حتى الأقمار الصناعية وشبكة الدفاع النووي.
All of these things are made possible
وكل تلك الأشياء أصبحت ممكنة
because of computers,
بفضل الحواسيب، وبالتالي بفضل السيبرانية،
and when something goes wrong,
وعندما لا تسير الأمور بشكل جيد،
cyber can make all of these things impossible.
السيبرانية تجعل من كل ذلك أمرا مستحيلا.
But that's where I step in.
وعند هذه النقطة أتدخل أنا.
A big part of my job is defending all of these things,
فجزء كبير من عملي هو منع حدوث ذلك،
keeping them working,
وإبقائها تعمل بشكل جيد،
but once in a while, part of my job is to break one of these things,
لكن أحيانا، تكون مهمتي كسر واحدة منها،
because cyber isn't just about defense,
لأن السيبرانية ليست مكان للدفاع فقط،
it's also about offense.
بل للهجوم أيضا.
We're entering an age where we talk about
نحن في عصر نتحدث فيه
cyberweapons.
عن الأسلحة السيبرانية.
In fact, so great is the potential for cyber offense
الواقع أنه نظرا للقدرة الكبيرة
Warfare.
نعم للحرب.
It's not necessarily a bad thing.
وهذا ليس بالضرورة أمرا سيئا.
On the one hand, it means we have whole new front
هذا يعني أنه لدينا من جهة جبهة جديدة كاملة
on which we need to defend ourselves,
حيث نحتاج للدفاع عن أنفسنا،
but on the other hand,
ومن جهة أخرى،
it means we have a whole new way to attack,
لدينا وسيلة جديدة للهجوم،
a whole new way to stop evil people
وسيلة جديدة بالكامل لمنع الأشرار
from doing evil things.
من القيام بأمورهم الشريرة.
So let's consider an example of this
دعونا نأخذ مثالا عن ذلك
that's completely theoretical.
بشكل افتراضي فقط.
Suppose a terrorist wants to blow up a building,
لنفترض أن إرهابيا يريد تفجير مبنى،
and he wants to do this again and again
وأنه يريد فعل ذلك مرارا وتكرارا بالمستقبل.
So he doesn't want to be in that building when it explodes.
وأنه لا يريد أن يكون بالمبنى عند انفجاره.
He's going to use a cell phone
لدى سيستخدم هاتفا خلوي
as a remote detonator.
كجهاز تفجير عن بعد.
Now, it used to be the only way we had
وكانت الطريقة الوحيدة التي اعتدنا
to stop this terrorist
استخدامها لإيقاف ذلك الإرهابي
was with a hail of bullets and a car chase,
هي بأمطار من الرصاص ومطاردة بالسيارة،
but that's not necessarily true anymore.
لكن لم يعد هذا ضروريا بعد الآن.
We're entering an age where we can stop him
فقد دخلنا عصرا حيث يمكننا إيقافه
with the press of a button
بكبسة زر فقط، عن بُعْد 1600 كلم،
because whether he knew it or not,
لأنه سواء كان يعلم ذلك أو لا،
as soon as he decided to use his cell phone,
بمجرد أن قرر استخدام هاتفه الخلوي،
he stepped into the realm of cyber.
فقد دخل عالم السيبرانية.
A well-crafted cyber attack could break into his phone,
يمكن اقتحام هاتفه بهجوم سيبراني مُحْكَم،
disable the overvoltage protections on his battery,
وتعطيل حماية الجهد الزائد ببطاريته،
drastically overload the circuit,
وتحميل دارته بشكل كبير،
cause the battery to overheat, and explode.
لترتفع حرارة البطارية وتنفجر.
No more phone, no more detonator,
لا هاتف لا مُفَجِّر عن بُعد.
maybe no more terrorist,
وربما لا إرهابي،
all with the press of a button
الكل بكبسة زر، عن بُعد مئات الأمتار.
So how does this work?
إذا، كيف يعمل ذلك؟
It all comes back to those ones and zeros.
كل ذلك مرتبط بتلك الآحاد والأصفار.
Binary information makes your phone work,
المعلومات الثنائية تجعل هاتفكم يعمل،
and used correctly, it can make your phone explode.
وباستخدامها بشكل صحيح، يمكنها جعله ينفجر.
So when you start to look at cyber from this perspective,
عندما تنظر إلى السيبرانية بهذا الشكل،
spending your life sifting through binary information
فإن قضاء حياتك بغربلة المعلومات الثنائية
starts to seem kind of exciting.
يبدو أمرا مثيرا.
But here's the catch: This is hard,
لكن هناك فخ: فهو أمر صعب،
really, really hard,
جد جد صعب،
and here's why.
وهذا هو السبب.
Think about everything you have on your cell phone.
فكروا في كل ما هو مخزن على هاتفكم الخلوي.
You've got the pictures you've taken.
بكل الصور التي التقطتموها.
You've got the music you listen to.
والموسيقى التي تسمعونها.
You've got your contacts list,
وقائمة الأرقام الهاتفية وبريدكم الإلكتروني
and behind all of this is the software, the code,
وخلف كل ذلك هناك البرنامج والبرمجة
that controls your phone,
اللذين يتحكمان في هاتفكم،
and somewhere, buried inside of that code,
وفي مكان ما داخل تلك البرمجة،
is a tiny piece that controls your battery,
توجد قطعة صغيرة تتحكم في بطاريتكم،
and that's what I'm really after,
وهذا ما أصبو إليه بشدة،
but all of this, just a bunch of ones and zeros,
لكن كل هذا، عبارة عن حزمة آحاد وأصفار،
In cyber, we call this finding a needle in a stack of needles,
وهذا ما نسميه في السيبرانية
because everything pretty much looks alike.
لأن كل شيء فيها متشابه لحد كبير.
I'm looking for one key piece,
أنا أبحث عن القطعة المفتاح،
but it just blends in with everything else.
لكنها مُمَوَّهة بما حولها.
So let's step back from this theoretical situation
فلنترك جانبا هذا الموقف النظري
of making a terrorist's phone explode,
عن تفجير هاتف الإرهابي،
and look at something that actually happened to me.
ولنفحص أمرا حدث معي.
my job always starts with sitting down
عملي يبدأ دائما بالجلوس على مقعد
with a whole bunch of binary information,
أمام حزمة كاملة من المعلومات الثنائية،
and I'm always looking for one key piece
وأنا دائما أبحث عن القطعة المفتاح
to do something specific.
للقيام بشيء محدد.
In this case, I was looking for a very advanced,
في هذه الحالة، كنت أبحث عن جزء جد متقدم
very high-tech piece of code
وجد معقد من البرمجة
that I knew I could hack,
كنت أعلم بأني قادر على قرصنته،
but it was somewhere buried
لكنها كانت مختبئة في مكان ما
inside of a billion ones and zeroes.
داخل ملايين الآحاد والأصفار.
Unfortunately for me, I didn't know
لسوء حظي، لم أكن أعلم
quite what I was looking for.
ما كنت أبحث عنه.
I didn't know quite what it would look like,
ولم أكن أدري ما هو شكله،
which makes finding it really, really hard.
مما يجعل من العثور عليه أمرا جد صعب.
When I have to do that, what I have to do
وعندما يكون علي القيام بذلك،
is basically look at various pieces
يتوجب علي في الأساس البحث عن قطع مختلفة
of this binary information,
من المعلومات الثنائية وأحاول فك كل قطعة،
So after a while, I thought I had found the piece
وبعد فترة، اعتقدت أني وجدت القطعة المنشودة.
I thought maybe this was it.
وفكرت أنها ربما كانت هي.
It seemed to be about right, but I couldn't quite tell.
كل شيء بدا على ما يرام، لكن لم أكن متأكدا.
I couldn't tell what those ones and zeros represented.
لم أكن متأكدا من معنى تلك الآحاد والأصفار.
So I spent some time trying to put this together,
لذا قضيت بعض الوقت محاولا تجميعها معا،
but wasn't having a whole lot of luck,
لكن لم يحالفني الكثير من الحظ،
and finally I decided,
وفي النهاية قررت، بأني أستطيع القيام بذلك.
I'm going to come in on a weekend,
وأني سأعمل عليه بنهاية الأسبوع،
and I'm not going to leave
وأني لن أستسلم إلى أن أعرف معنى تلك القطع.
So that's what I did. I came in on a Saturday morning,
وهذا ما فعلته. جئت صباح يوم السبت،
and about 10 hours in, I sort of had all the pieces to the puzzle.
وبعد 10 ساعات من العمل،
I just didn't know how they fit together.
لم يبقي سوى معرفة كيف أركبها.
I didn't know what these ones and zeros meant.
لم أكن أدري ما تعنيه هذه الآحاد والأصفار.
At the 15-hour mark,
وعند الساعة 15،
I started to get a better picture of what was there,
بدأت أحصل على صورة أفضل عما كان أمامي،
but I had a creeping suspicion
لكن كان لدي شك يتزايد بأن ما كنت أنظر إليه
was not at all related to what I was looking for.
لم تكن له أية علاقة بما كنت أبحث عنه.
By 20 hours, the pieces started to come together
وقبل الساعة 20، بدأت القطع
very slowly — (Laughter) —
تتجمع ببطء — (ضحك) —
and I was pretty sure I was going down
وعند هذه اللحظة كنت متأكدا بأنني
After 30 hours in the lab,
وبعد 30 ساعة بالمختبر،
I figured out exactly what I was looking at,
تمكنت بالضبط من معرفة ما كنت أنظر إليه،
and I was right, it wasn't what I was looking for.
وكنت محقا، لم يكن ذلك ما أبحث عنه.
I spent 30 hours piecing together
قضيت 30 ساعة وأنا أُجَمِّع
the ones and zeros that formed a picture of a kitten.
الآحاد والأصفار التي تكون صورة هرة صغيرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I wasted 30 hours of my life searching for this kitten
ضيعت 30 ساعة من حياتي أبحث عن هذه الهرة
that had nothing at all to do
التي ليس لها أية علاقة
with what I was trying to accomplish.
بما كنت أحاول القيام به.
So I was frustrated, I was exhausted.
لذا أصبت بالإحباط، وكنت جد مرهق.
After 30 hours in the lab, I probably smelled horrible.
بعد 30 ساعة في المختبر، لابد أني كنت أفوح.
But instead of just going home
لكن بدلا من أن أعود للمنزل
and calling it quits, I took a step back
والاستسلام، أخذت خطوة إلى الوراء
and asked myself, what went wrong here?
وسألت نفسي، ما الخطأ الذي ارتكبته هنا؟
How could I make such a stupid mistake?
كيف ارتكبت خطأ غبيا كهذا؟
I'm really pretty good at this.
أنا جيد في هذا المجال.
I do this for a living.
هذا هو عملي. - فما الذي حصل؟
Well I thought, when you're looking at information at this level,
أظن أنه عند بحثك في معلومات بهذا المستوى،
it's so easy to lose track of what you're doing.
يكون من السهل جدا أن تفقد طريقك نحو هدفك.
It's easy to not see the forest through the trees.
وألا تشاهد الغابة من خلال الأشجار.
It's easy to go down the wrong rabbit hole
وأن تمشي في الطريق الخطأ
and waste a tremendous amount of time
وأن تضيع الكثير من الوقت
doing the wrong thing.
في القيام بالشيء الخطأ.
But I had this epiphany.
لكن كان لدي إحساس،
We were looking at the data completely incorrectly
أننا كنا ننظر للبيانات بشكل خاطئ تماما
since day one.
منذ اليوم الأول.
This is how computers think, ones and zeros.
هذه طريقة تفكير الحواسيب، الآحاد والأصفار.
It's not how people think,
وهي ليست الطريقة التي يفكر بها الناس
but we've been trying to adapt our minds
ولكن علينا محاولة تكييف عقولنا
to think more like computers
للتفكير أكثر مثل الحواسيب
so that we can understand this information.
لنتمكن من فهم تلك المعلومات.
Instead of trying to make our minds fit the problem,
بدلا من محاولة تتكيف عقولنا مع المشكل،
we should have been making the problem
علينا جعل المشكل يتكيف مع عقولنا،
because our brains have a tremendous potential
لأن عقولنا تمتلك قدرة هائلة
for analyzing huge amounts of information,
لتحليل كم هائل من المعلومات
just not like this.
ولكن ليس بهذه الطريقة.
So what if we could unlock that potential
ماذا لو تمكننا من تحرير هذه القدرة
to the right kind of information?
بتحويلها للنوع المناسب من المعلومات فقط؟
So with these ideas in mind,
انطلقت وتلك الأفكار برأسي من مختبري بالعمل
to my basement lab at home,
ركضا نحو مختبري بالمنزل،
which looked pretty much the same.
اللذين يشبهان بعضهما كثيرا.
The main difference is, at work,
لكن الاختلاف الكبير هو، في العمل،
I'm surrounded by cyber materials,
أنا محاط بأدوات سيبرانية،
and cyber seemed to be the problem in this situation.
ويبدو أن بهذه الحالة السيبرانية هي المشكل.
At home, I'm surrounded by everything else I've ever learned.
في المنزل، أنا محاط بكل شيء آخر تعلمته.
So I poured through every book I could find,
انكببت على كل كتاب عثرت عليه،
every idea I'd ever encountered,
والأفكار التي رأيتها من قبل،
to see how could we translate a problem
لمعرفة كيف يمكن أن نحول مشكلا
from one domain to something completely different?
من مجال محدد لشيء مختلف تماما؟
The biggest question was,
السؤال الكبير كان، إلى ماذا نود تحويلها؟
What do our brains do perfectly naturally
ما الأمر الذي تفعله عقولنا بشكل طبيعي
that we could exploit?
ويمكننا استغلاله؟
My answer was vision.
كان جوابي هو الرؤية.
We have a tremendous capability to analyze visual information.
لدينا قدرة هائلة لتحليل المعلومات البصرية.
We can combine color gradients, depth cues,
بمكننا الجمع بين تدرجات الألوان، وعمقها
all sorts of these different signals
وجميع أنواع تلك الإشارات المختلفة
into one coherent picture of the world around us.
الموجودة بصورة واحدة لما يحيط بنا.
That's incredible.
هذا لا يصدق.
So if we could find a way to translate
إذا عثرنا على طريقة لتحويل
these binary patterns to visual signals,
هذه النماذج الثنائية إلى إشارات بصرية،
we could really unlock the power of our brains
سنتمكن بالفعل من استغلال قوة عقولنا
to process this stuff.
لمعالجة هذه الأمور.
So I started looking at the binary information,
لدى بدأت بالنظر إلى المعلومات الثنائية،
and I asked myself, what do I do
وسألت نفسي، ما الذي أفعله
when I first encounter something like this?
عندما أواجه شيئا كهذا؟
And the very first thing I want to do,
وأول ما أرغب في القيام به،
the very first question I want to answer,
أول سؤال أرغب في الإجابة عليه،
is what is this?
ما هذا؟
I don't care what it does, how it works.
لا أهتم لما يفعله، وكيف يعمل.
All I want to know is, what is this?
كل ما أريد معرفته هو، ما هذا؟
And the way I can figure that out
والطريقة التي يمكنني بها معرفة ذلك
is by looking at chunks,
هو بالنظر إلى قطع كبيرة،
sequential chunks of binary information,
قطع كبيرة متتالية من المعلومات الثنائية،
and I look at the relationships between those chunks.
والنظر إلى العلاقة التي تربط تلك القطع.
When I gather up enough of these sequences,
عندما أجمع ما يكفي من تلك المتتاليات،
I begin to get an idea of exactly
تبدأ فكرة دقيقة في التكون لدي
what this information must be.
عن ماهية تلك المعلومات.
So let's go back to that
دعونا نعد للخلف
blow up the terrorist's phone situation.
حيث نفجر هاتف الإرهابي.
This is what English text looks like
هذا ما يبدو عليه نص بالإنجليزية
at a binary level.
في شكله الثنائي.
This is what your contacts list would look like
هذا هو شكل قائمة أرقام هواتفكم
if I were examining it.
إذا قمت بفحصها.
It's really hard to analyze this at this level,
من الصعب فحص ذلك عند هذا المستوى،
but if we take those same binary chunks
لكن إن أخذنا نفس القطع الثنائية
that I would be trying to find,
التي أحاول العثور عليها،
and instead translate that
وبدلا من تحويلها إلى تمثيل بصري،
translate those relationships,
حولنا العلاقات التي تربطها،
this is what we get.
هذا ما نحصل عليه.
This is what English text looks like
هذا ما يبدو عليه نص بالإنجليزية
from a visual abstraction perspective.
من منظور تجريدي بصري.
All of a sudden,
وفجأة، تظهر لنا جميعا نفس المعلومات
that was in the ones and zeros,
التي كانت يالآحاد والأصفار،
but show us it in an entirely different way,
لكنها تظهرها لنا بطريقة مختلفة تماما،
a way that we can immediately comprehend.
بطريقة يمكننا أن نفهمها على الفور.
We can instantly see all of the patterns here.
يمكننا فورا رؤية كل النماذج هنا.
It takes me seconds to pick out patterns here,
ويتطلب الأمر بضع ثوان لاختيار نماذج من هنا،
but hours, days, to pick them out
لكن ساعات وأيام لاختيارها
in ones and zeros.
بين الآحاد والأصفار.
It takes minutes for anybody to learn
ويتطلب الأمر دقائق من أحدهم لمعرفة
what these patterns represent here,
ما الذي تمثله تلك النماذج هنا،
but years of experience in cyber
لكن سنوات من الخبرة في السيبرانية
to learn what those same patterns represent
لمعرفة ما تمثله نفس تلك الأنماط
in ones and zeros.
عندما تكون بين الآحاد والأصفار.
So this piece is caused by
تتكون هذه القطعة
lower case letters followed by lower case letters
من أحرف صغيرة تلو أحرف صغيرة
inside of that contact list.
داخل قائمة أرقام الهاتف تلك.
This is upper case by upper case,
وهذا حرف كبير يتلوه حرف كبير،
upper case by lower case, lower case by upper case.
حرف كبير يتلوه حرف صغير والعكس.
This is caused by spaces. This is caused by carriage returns.
هذا بسبب الفراغ. وهذا بالرجوع إلى السطر.
We can go through every little detail
يمكننا مراجعة كل التفاصيل الصغيرة
of the binary information in seconds,
بالمعلومات الثنائية في بضعة ثوان،
as opposed to weeks, months, at this level.
عوض أسابيع وأشهر عند هذا المستوى.
This is what an image looks like
هذا ما تبدو عليه صورة من هاتفكم الخلوي.
But this is what it looks like
ولكن هذا شكلها التجريدي البصري.
This is what your music looks like,
هذا ما تبدو عليه موسيقاكم،
but here's its visual abstraction.
وهذا شكلها التجريدي البصري.
Most importantly for me,
وأهم شيء بالنسبة لي،
this is what the code on your cell phone looks like.
هذا ما تبدو عليه برمجة هاتفكم الخلوي.
This is what I'm after in the end,
ففي النهاية هذا ما أبحث عنه،
but this is its visual abstraction.
وهذا شكلها التجريدي البصري.
I could spend weeks trying to find this
قد أقضي أسابيع وأنا أبحث عليه
in ones and zeros,
بين الآحاد والأصفار،
but it takes me seconds to pick out
لكن اختيار تجريد بصري كهذا
a visual abstraction like this.
يتطلب مني بضع ثوان فقط.
One of those most remarkable parts about all of this
لكن الأمر المذهل في كل هذا
is it gives us an entirely new way to understand
هو أنه يقدم لنا طريقة جديدة تماما لفهم
new information, stuff that we haven't seen before.
معلومات جديدة، وأمور لم نرها من قبل.
So I know what English looks like at a binary level,
أنا أعرف الشكل الثنائي للإنجليزية،
and I know what its visual abstraction looks like,
وأعرف شكلها التجريدي البصري،
but I've never seen Russian binary in my entire life.
لكن لم أر في حياتي الشكل الثنائي للروسية.
It would take me weeks just to figure out
وقد أستغرق عدة أسابيع للتعرف على
what I was looking at from raw ones and zeros,
حزمة الآحاد والأصفار التي كنت أنظر إليها،
but because our brains can instantly pick up
ولأن عقولنا قادرة فورا على اختيار
and recognize these subtle patterns inside
والتعرف على تلك النماذج الخفية داخل
of these visual abstractions,
تلك الأشكال التجريدية البصرية،
we can unconsciously apply those
يمكننا بدون وعي تطبيق ذلك في مواقف جديدة.
So this is what Russian looks like
هذا ما تبدو عليه الروسية
in a visual abstraction.
في شكلها التجريدي البصري.
Because I know what one language looks like,
لأني أعرف ما تبدو عليه لغة واحدة،
I can recognize other languages
أستطيع التعرف على اللغات الأخرى
even when I'm not familiar with them.
حتى وإن لم أكن أتحدثها.
This is what a photograph looks like,
هذا ما تبدو عليه الصور،
but this is what clip art looks like.
لكن هذا هو شكل قصاصة فنية.
This is what the code on your phone looks like,
وهذا ما تبدو عليه برمجة هاتفكم،
but this is what the code on your computer looks like.
لكن هذا ما تبدو عليه برمجة حاسوبكم.
Our brains can pick up on these patterns
يمكن لعقولنا أن تلتقط تلك النماذج
in ways that we never could have
بطرق لم نفعلها من قبل
from looking at raw ones and zeros.
عند النظر إلى حزمة الآحاد والأصفار.
But we've really only scratched the surface
لكن لم نكشف سوى قمة الجبل الجليدي
of what we can do with this approach.
مما يمكننا فعله بفضل هذه المقاربة.
We've only begun to unlock the capabilities
لقد بدأنا للتو باستغلال قدرات
of our minds to process visual information.
عقولنا في معالجة المعلومات البصرية.
If we take those same concepts and translate them
إن أخذنا نفس تلك الأفكار وحولناها
into three dimensions instead,
لتصبح ثلاثية الأبعاد،
we find entirely new ways of making sense of information.
سنجد طرقا جديدة لإعطاء معنى لتلك المعلومات.
In seconds, we can pick out every pattern here.
وفي ثوان، يمكننا التعرف على أي نموذج هنا.
we can see the cross associated with code.
يمكننا رؤية خط التقاطع المتعلق بالبرمجة.
We can see cubes associated with text.
والمكعبات المتعلقة بالنص.
We can even pick up the tiniest visual artifacts.
ويمكننا حتى التعرف على أصغر شيء بصري.
Things that would take us weeks,
الأمور التي كانت لتستغرق منا أسابيع
months to find in ones and zeroes,
وشهورا للعثور عليها بين الآحاد والأصفار،
are immediately apparent
تظهر الآن بشكل فوري
in some sort of visual abstraction,
في نوع من التجريد البصري،
and as we continue to go through this
وباستمرارنا في دراسته
and throw more and more information at it,
وإضافة المزيد والمزيد من المعلومات إليه،
what we find is that we're capable of processing
سنجد أنفسنا قادرين على معالجة
billions of ones and zeros
الملايير من الآحاد والأصفار في بضعة ثوان
just by using our brain's built-in ability
فقط باستخدام القدرة المدمجة بعقولنا
to analyze patterns.
لتحليل تلك النماذج.
So this is really nice and helpful,
هذا جميل ومفيد حقا،
but all this tells me is what I'm looking at.
لكن كل ما يخبرني به، هو ما أنظر إليه.
So at this point, based on visual patterns,
بهذه المرحلة، اعتمادا على النماذج البصرية،
I can find the code on the phone.
أستطيع العثور على برمجة الهاتف.
But that's not enough to blow up a battery.
لكن هذا لا يكفي لتفجير البطارية.
The next thing I need to find is the code
الشيء التالي الذي ينبغي أن أجده هو
that controls the battery, but we're back
البرمجة المتحكمة بالبطارية، وبهذا نعود
to the needle in a stack of needles problem.
إلى مشكل الإبرة بكومة من الإبر.
That code looks pretty much like all the other code
فهذه البرمجة تشبه لحد كبير البرمجات الأخرى
on that system.
بهذا النظام.
So I might not be able to find the code that controls the battery,
قد لا أعثر على البرمجة المُتَحَكِّمَة بالبطارية،
but there's a lot of things that are very similar to that.
لكن هناك الكثير من الأشياء المشابهة لذلك.
You have code that controls your screen,
فلديكم مثلا البرمجة المتحكمة بشاشتكم،
that controls your buttons, that controls your microphones,
والمتحكمة بأزراركم وميكروفوناتكم،
so even if I can't find the code for the battery,
لذا حتى وإن لم أعثر على برمجة البطارية،
I bet I can find one of those things.
أراهن على أني سأجد واحدة من تلك الأشياء.
So the next step in my binary analysis process
المرحلة المقبلة بعملية التحليل الثنائية
is to look at pieces of information
هي النظر إلى قطع المعلومات
that are similar to each other.
المتشابهة فيما بينها.
It's really, really hard to do at a binary level,
من الصعب القيام بذلك بشكلها الثنائي،
but if we translate those similarities to a visual abstraction instead,
لكن إن حولنا تلك التشابهات إلى تجريد بصري،
I don't even have to sift through the raw data.
لن يكون علي حتى أن أدقق بالبيانات الخام.
All I have to do is wait for the image to light up
كل ما علي فعله هو انتظار ظهور الصورة
to see when I'm at similar pieces.
لمعرفة متى تكون لدي قطع مماثلة.
I follow these strands of similarity like a trail of bread crumbs
بحيث أتتبع تلك التشابهات كفتات الخبز
to find exactly what I'm looking for.
لأعثر بالضبط على ما أبحث عليه.
So at this point in the process,
وعند هذه المرحلة من المعالجة،
I've located the code
حددت البرمجة المسؤولة عن التحكم بالبطارية،
but that's still not enough to blow up a phone.
لكن ذلك ما يزال غير كاف لتفجير الهاتف.
The last piece of the puzzle
آخر قطعة بالأحجية
is understanding how that code
هي فهم طريقة تحكم تلك البرمجة ببطاريتكم.
For this, I need to identify
للقيام بذلك أنا بحاجة لتحديد
very subtle, very detailed relationships
العلاقات الدقيقة والمفصلة
within that binary information,
التي تربط بين هذه المعلومات الثنائية،
another very hard thing to do
وهذا أمر آخر يصعب القيام به
when looking at ones and zeros.
عند النظر للآحاد والأصفار.
But if we translate that information
لكن إن حولنا هذه المعلومات
into a physical representation,
لعرض محسوس،
we can sit back and let our visual cortex do all the hard work.
يمكننا الجلوس وترك القشرة البصرية
It can find all the detailed patterns,
يمكنها العثور على جميع النماذج بالتفصيل،
all the important pieces, for us.
وعلى كل القطع المهمة، بالنسبة لنا.
It can find out exactly how the pieces of that code
يمكنها معرفة كيفية عمل قطع هذه البرمجة
work together to control that battery.
معا للتحكم بتلك البطارية.
All of this can be done in a matter of hours,
كل ذلك يمكن أن يتم في غضون ساعات،
whereas the same process
في حين أن نفس العملية
would have taken months in the past.
كانت لتستغرق أشهرا في الماضي.
This is all well and good
كل هذا جيد ومفيد من الناحية النظرية
in a theoretical blow up a terrorist's phone situation.
لتفجير هاتف الإرهابي.
I wanted to find out if this would really work
كنت أود معرفة ما إذا كان هذا سينجح
in the work I do every day.
في عملي اليومي.
So I was playing around with these same concepts
كنت ألعب بنفس تلك الأفكار
with some of the data I've looked at in the past,
مع بعض البيانات التي بحثت عنها من قبل،
and yet again, I was trying to find
ومرة أخرى، كنت أحاول العثور
a very detailed, specific piece of code
على قطعة معينة ومفصلة من البرمجة
inside of a massive piece of binary information.
داخل قطعة ضخمة من المعلومات الثنائية.
So I looked at it at this level,
لذا كنت أنظر إليها في هذه المرحلة،
thinking I was looking at the right thing,
معتقدا بأني أنظر إلى الشيء الصحيح،
only to see this doesn't have
لألاحظ بأنها لا تملك
the connectivity I would have expected
الربط الذي كنت أتوقعه
for the code I was looking for.
بالنسبة للبرمجة التي كنت أبحث عنها.
In fact, I'm not really sure what this is,
في الواقع، لم أكن متأكدا مما هو،
but when I stepped back a level
لكن عندما تراجعت خطوة
and looked at the similarities within the code
ونظرت إلى التشابهات داخل البرمجة
I saw, this doesn't have similarities
لاحظت بأنه لا توجد تشابهات
like any code that exists out there.
مع أي برمجة موجودة.
I can't even be looking at code.
حتى أنه يستحيل أن تكون تلك برمجة.
In fact, from this perspective,
في الواقع، من هذه الناحية،
I could tell, this isn't code.
يمكنني القول، بأنه ليست برمجة.
This is an image of some sort.
إنها صورة من نوع ما.
And from here, I can see,
ومن هنا، يمكنني أن ألاحظ،
it's not just an image, this is a photograph.
بأنها ليست صورة وحسب، بل صورة فوتوغرافية.
Now that I know it's a photograph,
ولأني أعلم بأنها صورة،
I've got dozens of other binary translation techniques
كان لدي العشرات من تقنيات التحويل الثنائية
to visualize and understand that information,
لمشاهدة وفهم هذه المعلومات،
so in a matter of seconds, we can take this information,
وفي ثوان، يمكننا أخذ تلك المعلومات،
shove it through a dozen other visual translation techniques
ونخضعها لعشرات التقنيات للتحويل البصري
in order to find out exactly what we were looking at.
من أجل أن نعرف بالضبط ما ننظر إليه.
I saw — (Laughter) —
فرأيت — (ضحك) —
it was that darn kitten again.
كانت تلك الهرة الصغيرة مرة أخرى.
All this is enabled
كل ذلك كان ممكنا
because we were able to find a way
لأننا كنا قادرين على إيجاد طريقة
to translate a very hard problem
لتحويل ذلك المشكل العصيب
to something our brains do very naturally.
لشيء تقوم به عقولنا بشكل طبيعي.
So what does this mean?
فماذا يعني ذلك؟
Well, for kittens, it means
بالنسبة للقطط، هذا يعني
no more hiding in ones and zeros.
لا مزيد من الاختباء بين الآحاد والأصفار.
For me, it means no more wasted weekends.
بالنسبة لي، لا مزيد من الأسابيع الضائعة.
For cyber, it means we have a radical new way
وللسيبرانية، طريقة جديدة تماما
to tackle the most impossible problems.
لمعالجة المشاكل الأكثر تعقيدا.
It means we have a new weapon
هذا يعني لدينا سلاح جديد
in the evolving theater of cyber warfare,
على المسرح المتطور للحرب السيبرانية،
but for all of us,
ولنا جميعا أن المهندسين السيبرانيين
now have the ability to become first responders
بإمكانهم أن يكونوا أول خط دفاع
in emergency situations.
خلال المواقف الخطيرة.
When seconds count,
فقد حررنا وسائل إيقاف الأشرار،
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)